"How to Keep Your Microbiome
Healthy with Prebiotic Foods"
If you look at the classics, the
most frequently cited articles
in the scientific nutrition
literature, the original
glycemic index paper comes out
at #10, cited over a thousand times.
Learning about fruit, vegetables, and
cancer prevention was a hallmark.
But hitting the top 5,
cited more than 2,000 times,
“Dietary modulation of
the human microbiom
introducing the concept of prebiotics.”
Prebiotics are the food
components that feed and nourish
the good bacteria in our gut,
like fiber and resistant starch.
In general, eating
high-fiber plant foods is
a good foundation for
a prebiotic-rich diet.
Once upon a time, fiber
was just thought of as just
the undigested component
of foods, known only for
bulking up stools and
keeping our bowels regular.
Then, we discovered an array
of receptors in the body in which
fiber breakdown products
fit in like a lock-and-key.
We feed our good bacteria
with fiber, and they feed us
right back, munching the fiber
and creating short chain
fatty acids that get absorbed
into our bloodstream and
fit into these receptors that
are expressed on immune cells
and generally mediate a direct
anti-inﬂammatory effect.
So, the reason for lower
systemic inﬂammation in
plant-based eaters may not
just be due to the abundance
of anti-inﬂammatory molecules
in plant foods or the
avoidance of proinﬂammatory
molecules in animal foods,
but from the production of
anti-inflammatory molecules
from scratch by our good gut
bugs when we feed them fiber.
Just to give you an idea how
protective fiber-rich foods
can be, those randomized to
get advice to eat fiber-rich
plant foods during radiation
therapy for cancer didn’t just
experience reduced toxicity
during the treatments,
but even a full year later.
Indeed, the benefits of fiber are supported
by more than a century of research.
Prospective studies show
striking reductions in death
from all causes put together,
including “total cancer deaths,
total cardiovascular disease
deaths and incidence,
stroke incidence, and
incidence of colorectal,
breast, and esophageal cancer.”
And “dose-response
relationships” suggest that
the more the better, in
terms of protecting against
heart attacks and stroke,
type 2 diabetes, and cancer.
So, at a minimum, fiber
intakes should be no less than
25–29 grams per day,with additional benefits
likely to accrue with higher intakes.
Yet, the average American only consumes
about 16 grams of ﬁber per day.
We have coevolved over
millennia with gut bacteria
to the point of reliance
on our good gut bugs,
a kind of symbiosis for
ﬁber digestion and
the production of short chain fatty acids,
and even certain vitamins.
Yet, we’re not holding up
our end of the bargain.
We’re supposed to be providing up
to 100 or so grams of fiber a day,
and we are barely passing
along a measly 16 grams.
The simplest solution, the
simplest approach to remedy this
lack of dietary fiber is
to encourage consumption
of whole food plant-based nutrition.